Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is מ"א mem aleph
41, we are a bit behind, we are about six lines from
the top on מ"א עמוד ב', mem amud bet, we'll see if
we can catch up today. We are in the middle of a
very important discussion about שעטנז shatnez and ציצית, tzitzit, where specifically the
case about a linen garment and do we put ציצית tzitzit in
it or do we put תכלת tekhelet in it? בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says no, בית הלל Beit Hillel says yes, then a whole
discussion in the גמרא Gemara which seems to be that even according
to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, which in principle the answer is yes,
in practice the answer is no, we don't, and the reason basically
boils down to the fact that we're afraid that people will do
it in a way that it would not be halachically valid תכלת,
tekhelet, that they'll use the wrong color, and or in the end
the גמרא Gemara said a concern that the garment would tear and
they would sew it up again and it would be תעשה ולא
מן העשוי ta’aseh ve-lo min he-asui and it would not be יוצא
yotzei the מצוה mitzvah and when you're not יוצא yotzei the מצוה
mitzvah of תכלת tekhelet or of ציצית tzitzit altogether, then you're actually
violating and wearing שעטנז. shatnez. In practice, they said do not put
תכלת tekhelet strings in this linen garment, do not have שעטנז shatnez
in your ציצית, tzitzit,
and I should say that תוספות Tosafot reads that סוגיא sugya that
not only not to put תכלת tekhelet in but not to put
ציצית tzitzit in it at all. We'll see a little bit of
that more later today. Okay, but anyway that was the answer and
for one reason the גמרא Gemara said was because of a concern
of I guess we'll just pick up here, רבא, Rava, we'll pick
up,
we'll quickly go back of what we did yesterday, three lines from
the
top, אלא אמר רבא הא מלתא אמי ואיתמר במערבא משמיה דרבי זירא
כוותי. ella amar Rava ha milta ami ve-itmar b'ma'arava mishmei de-Rabbi Zera
kevasinei. So I'm not going to fully unpack that, we did that
yesterday, but the גמרא Gemara will tear within three finger widths you
know from the corner and then you'll sew it back up and
the ציצית tzitzit that were already on the corner will now be
created as a תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta’aseh ve-lo min he-asui and
you won't be יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah and then you'll be
over שעטנז shatnez because you're not being יוצא yotzei the מצוה. mitzvah.
And because of that or related to that שרי רבי זירא לסדיניה,
shari Rabbi Zera le-sadinei, that רבי זירא Rabbi Zera untook his, you
know, the ציצית, tzitzit, untied the ציצית tzitzit from his garment which
was a linen garment because of this concern of that we're not
supposed to be wearing שעטנז shatnez even when we're being יוצא yotzei
the מצוה mitzvah because something might go wrong.
Okay, that's what we got up to yesterday. רב
זירא Rav Zera אמר, amar, now רב זירא Rav Zera who seems
to be different from רבי זירא, Rabbi Zera, רב זירא Rav Zera
said: גזירה נמי משום כסות לילה, gezeirah nami mishum kesut laila, a
different concern. Not that it'll be פסול, pasul, but that you'll have
your ציצית tzitzit on and when you're having, you know, your שעטנז
shatnez on, which is okay if you're doing the מצוה, mitzvah, but
then you'll come to put it on a garment that's worn at
night, that's designated for night only, like pajamas, and there those, such
garments are not obligated in ציצית. tzitzit. So again, you will now
create for your linen pajamas you'll put ציצית tzitzit on them and
those will be, and then it will be at with the wool
תכלת tekhelet and that will be a problem of שעטנז shatnez because
garments that are designated for the nighttime are not obligated. And because
of the concern that if so, therefore we don't even let you
put it on day garments because you'll come to put it on
night garments. Okay,
ואמר רבא ve-amar Rava and רבא Rava said: הא מלתא אמי ואיתמר
במערבא משמיה דרבי זירא כוותי, ha milta ami ve-itmar b'ma'arava mishmei de-Rabbi
Zera kevasinei, this is echoing what we said before, that רבא Rava
said I said this thing and then in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
they said, you know, this in the name of רבי זירא, Rabbi
Zera, exactly what I've been teaching here in בבל. Bavel. And what
is this?
משמיה כוותי, mishmei kevasinei,
היא של בגד וכנפיה של עור חייבת. hi shel beged ve-knafeha shel
or chayavet. If the garment is leather and the corners are of,
excuse me, the garment is wool and the corners are leather, leather
is not a material that's obligated in ציצית, tzitzit, the garment is
still חייב. chayav. It goes by the basic בגד, beged, not by
the כנף, knaf, even though you put the ציצית tzitzit on the
כנף. knaf. היא של עור וכנפיה של בגד פטורה hi shel or
ve-knafeha shel beged petura and the reverse, if the garment is leather
and the corners are cloth, wool, פטורה, petura, it's exempt. מאי טעמא?
עיקר בגד בעינן, mai ta’ama? ikkar beged ba’inan, we need the fundamental
בגד beged to be the material that is obligated in ציצית. tzitzit.
Okay and once that's true, if the corners are leather that does
not exempt it. רב אחאי אזל בתר כנף. Rav Achai azal batar
knaf. רב אחאי Rav Achai took the exact opposite position. He says
since it says על הכנף פתיל תכלת, al haknaf petil tchelet, so
you know, even though it says בגדיכם bigdeikhem and בגד beged and
so on, he focused on that the definition of the right material
to be obligated or not focuses on the כנף. knaf. All right,
אמר רבא אמר רב סחורה אמר רב הונא הדילה של שלש והשלימה
לארבע פסולה. amar Rava amar Rav Sechora amar Rav Huna hiddila shel
shalosh ve-hishlimah le-arba pesula. Now we're going to because we mentioned תעשה
ולא מן העשוי, ta’aseh ve-lo min he-asui, we're going to develop that
a little bit. So he said if you went ahead and you
put ציצית tzitzit on a garment that only had three corners, not
you put it on three of the four corners, it only had...
have three corners, so such a garment is not obligated in ציצית,
tzitzit, and then you made a fourth corner and now you added
ציצית tzitzit to the fourth corner. Okay, it's invalid. Why? משום תעשה
ולא מן העשוי mishum ta'aseh ve-lo min he-asuy because when you put
the it on the three corners, it was not yet obligated in
ציצית tzitzit the garment. So when it becomes obligated, that then you
say, oh look, and it already has ציצית. tzitzit. So the idea
that you should make, you know, you have to be, you know,
גדילים תעשה לך, gedilim ta'aseh lecha, you have to make it, right?
This is a similar דרשה drasha we have by סוכה, sukka, you
have to actively make it, it can't like be made automatically by
itself somehow. So here, you did not put ציצית tzitzit on an
obligated garment, you put ציצית tzitzit on an exempt garment, and then
when you made a corner, look, I have an obligated garment that
already has ציצית tzitzit on three of the corners. That doesn't count
as making the ציצית tzitzit on an obligated garment. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says מיתיבי, meitivei, I'm I'll challenge this. It seems like
we're not bothered with that by ציצית. tzitzit. חסידים הראשונים, Chasidim ha-Rishonim,
the, you know, early, you know, very righteous, pious people,
כיוון שארגו בה ג', keivan she-argu bah gimel, as soon as they
wove the garment that it was only like, you know, three fingerbreadths
wide, that was already significant, it already became defined as somewhat as
a garment, they would put ציצית tzitzit on it. They would put
ציצית tzitzit on let's say the edge, you know, not the edge
they were adding to obviously this was going to be a big
garment of who knows, like, you know, two feet long. But they
put the two ציצית tzitzit on the edge they began and then
they were going to put the other two when they finished to
make the garment till the full length. The only problem is is
that even though it might be considered a garment for laws of
like טומאה, tumah, we're going to see momentarily that, you know, for
ציצית tzitzit it has to be like a full-length garment, something that
you really wear to cloak yourself with. So it was not yet
obligated in ציצית. tzitzit. So it looks like you can put on
the ציצית tzitzit before the garment is obligated in ציצית. tzitzit. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, אימא כיוון שפצלו בה ג'. eima keivan
she-patzlu bah gimel. No,
the way you read that is not when they start making the
first three, but how you have to read that is that when
they were coming to the end of the edge, you know, you
start with edge one and then you're growing the garment and you're
weaving it and you're coming towards edge number two, like now it's
let's say at your full two feet length minus three fingerbreadths, so
that as soon as they got within three fingerbreadths of the of
finishing the second edge, that's when they put ציצית. tzitzit. The ציצית
tzitzit are, as we'll see, you know, implicit before, within three fingerbreadths
from the edge. So they got to two point nine fingerbreadths and
they put the ציצית tzitzit right there and then they're going to
add the other two point nine fingerbreadths to finish it off. So
the ציצית tzitzit will be within three fingerbreadths. But because the garment
is, what do you call it, is of requisite length when they're
almost done with it, they put the four ציצית tzitzit on an
obligated garment. Now we will find out later that you're not supposed
to put ציצית tzitzit exactly at the edge, and when they put
it, it was, you know, they still had three fingerbreadths to go,
so when they put it, they put it, you know, exactly at
the edge of that garment right there, but that might not be
an actual strict requirement, you know, בדיעבד, bedi'avad, and so on, we'll
see about that later. Anyway, that's what we're saying. It's when they
got within the last three, not when they were at the beginning
three. So it really was already a garment that was obligated in
ציצית. tzitzit. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says שפצלו בה ג' היו מטילין לתכלת. she-patzlu
bah gimel hayu matilin l'techelet. So now the גמרא Gemara is ומי
אמרינן תעשה ולא מן העשוי? u-mi amrinan ta'aseh ve-lo min he-asuy? We're
going to challenge this again. Are we really bothered with תעשה ולא
מן העשוי ta'aseh ve-lo min he-asuy when it comes to ציצית? tzitzit?
ואמר רב זירא, v'amar Rav Zeira, again here's a רב זירא, Rav
Zeira, he's had a lot to say about ציצית, tzitzit, הטיל למוטלת
כשרה. hitil le-muttelet keshera. If you went ahead and you put, you
know, ציצית tzitzit on something that already had that, excuse me,
yes, I was saying that right. If you went ahead and you
had a garment that already had ציצית tzitzit on it that's מוטלת,
muttelet, it already had it was on it already and you added,
you know, הטיל, hitil, you added an additional ציצית tzitzit on it.
So you on one of your four corners let's say you already
had one whole, you know, thing of ציצית tzitzit with the with
the wraps and the knots and the whole thing and then you
added a whole other thing of ציצית tzitzit in addition in that
corner. Okay, and then you were you cut off the ציצית tzitzit
that was already there, then that's going to be כשרה. keshera. Okay,
now why? The new ציצית tzitzit that you added was adding it
to a garment that was no longer not right now obligated. That
extra bundle of ציצית, tzitzit, that extra, you know, bunch there was
was not making it as when it was legitimate ציצית. tzitzit. And
since that's the case, when you cut off the the original ציצית
tzitzit that was there, then poof, the now legitimate ציצית tzitzit are
now on the garment without having been made. The second ציצית tzitzit
that you put on, because when you put it on it wasn't
a making, the garment wasn't obligated, and now
now automatically like
magically you already have ציצית tzitzit there, you did not put the
ציצית tzitzit on it when it needed to have those ציצית tzitzit
put on it. Now maybe you can make a distinction between a
garment that's obligated but the obligation is being satisfied compared to a
garment that isn't even obligated yet, okay, but let's see what the
גמרא Gemara how the גמרא Gemara answers this. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, והאמר רב זירא הטילו למטלית כשרה,
V'ha amar Rav Zeira
hitalu mitalot
k'sheira, אמר רבא. amar Rava.
So אמר רבא amar Rava says, השתא בבל תוסיף קאי מעשה לא
הוי. Hashta b'bal tosif kai ma-se lo havei.
So he says if you now are—excuse me I read that wrong,
it was not rhetorical. Let's do that again. אמר רבא, amar Rava,
השתא בבל תוסיף קאי מעשה לא הוי. Hashta b'bal tosif kai ma-se
lo havei. So רבא Rava says since you are transgressing בל תוסיף,
bal tosif, right? Classic בל תוסיף bal tosif for the Rabbis, do
not add to the מצוות mitzvot is adding another מצוה mitzvah object
to something that has a certain number of מצוה mitzvah objects, like
you take five מינים minim in ציצית, tzitzit, five compartments in your
תפילין. tefillin. So also, five ציצית tzitzit on a בגד beged that
only is required four ציצית. tzitzit. So when you put that extra
ציצית tzitzit on, okay, you are transgressing בל תוסיף. bal tosif. And
since you're transgressing בל תוסיף, bal tosif, it's like you did nothing,
מעשה לא הוי. ma-se lo havei. All right, it's like you did
nothing. And therefore, when you cut off the original ציצית, tzitzit,
then it's like that cutting off of the original ציצית tzitzit is
like you've now placed on this extra ציצית tzitzit and you've actually
now made this extra one into the legitimate ציצית. tzitzit. Not exactly
clear the logic here, right? רש"י Rashi says the distinction is if
you put it on a garment that's not obligated, then you've put
it on invalidly,
but it's considered an act, you've already done the act, it was
just not valid. And therefore, once you make it obligated, well, the
act was already done. Whereas in this case, because it was forbidden
to do it, so it's like the act—you didn't even do an
act. And therefore, when you cut off the original ציצית, tzitzit, that's
the making of it, that is the act. But I gotta tell
you, I really don't understand it. If anything, I would have said
when the garment isn't obligated, the act is meaningless, it's like no
act at all. When the garment is obligated and you're transgressing בל
תוסיף, bal tosif, the reason you're transgressing בל תוסיף bal tosif is
because you actually have added something and that act actually has weight.
It's invalid and in violation, but it actually has weight. Anyway, surprisingly,
רבא Rava here is saying exactly the opposite of that. And again,
you also could have made a distinction that when you put it
on something not obligated and then it becomes obligated, then it's like
it automatically happened, תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta-aseh v-lo min ha-asuy. Here,
the garment was obligated, so the act of putting on this extra
one could be considered actually not תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta-aseh v-lo
min ha-asuy. You know, that actually—the exact opposite of רבא. Rava. Not
it's no act at all and when you cut the ציצית tzitzit
that were already there, that is the act of putting these new
ציצית tzitzit on. The opposite. Because the garment was obligated, even though
it had four ציצית, tzitzit, you're putting a fifth ציצית tzitzit on
an obligated garment, that's a—you're doing a תעשה, ta-aseh, you're transgressing בל
תוסיף, bal tosif, but you're actively putting ציצית tzitzit on an obligated
garment. So I gotta tell you, I don't understand this answer. Anyway,
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
מתקיף לה רב פפא, Maskif la Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa
challenges this. ממי דגברא לאוסופי קמכוין דלמא לביטולי קמכוין ובל תוסיף ליכא
מעשה איכא. mi-mai d-gavra l-osufi qamichaven dilma l-vitulei qamichaven u-bal tosif leika
ma-se ika. So he doesn't disagree with the principle, but he just
says, you know, why should we assume that that definitely works? You're
saying it works because you're עובר over on בל תוסיף, bal tosif,
the first thing wasn't an act and it becomes an act later
when you cut the original ציצית tzitzit off. So he says, maybe
you weren't עובר over on בל תוסיף. bal tosif. If when you
put on that extra ציצית, tzitzit, you were intending to take off
what was already there and to negate what was already there,
you were going to cut it off, you wanted this new thing,
maybe the thing already there was fraying or who knows what, then
you're not transgressing בל תוסיף. bal tosif. It's like the thing that
was there originally has no weight.
Okay? And if that's true, you know, then it is an act.
Okay? But it is an act that right now though still isn't
meaningful. And when you cut off the fifth one—is it—the original one,
this will still be a תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta-aseh v-lo min
ha-asuy problem when you cut off the original one. Okay? So אמר
רב זירא, amar Rav Zeira, so according to you, רבא, Rava, you
said when the original thing doesn't count as an act, then it's
not a problem of תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta-aseh v-lo min ha-asuy
because then when you make it necessary, that is the act. When
you cut off the original one. But רב זירא Rav Zeira says
if you're intending to be מבטל mevattel the original one and not
to transgress בל תוסיף, bal tosif, and then you wouldn't transgress בל
תוסיף, bal tosif, then that makes the original thing you did an
act, but an act that wasn't yet valid, and then it would
be a תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta-aseh v-lo min ha-asuy problem when
you cut off the original one. Okay. So אמר רב זירא, amar
Rav Zeira, so we don't really know the
answer. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר
רבי זירא אמר רב Rav מתנה אמר שמואל Shmuel, תכלת techeiles אין
בה משום כלאים
ואפילו בטלית פטורה *Amar Rebbe Zeira amar Rav Masnah amar Shmuel techeiles
ein bah mishum kilayim v'afilu b'tallis peturah*.
Okay, so there's no problem of שעטנז Shatnez *shatnez* in ציצית Tzitzis,
*tzitzis*, you know, מעיקר הדין *me'ikar hadin*, that's what we've been talking
about, especially if you have, you know, תכלת techeiles *techeiles* in a
linen garment, okay, that's not a שעטנז Shatnez *shatnez* problem. Okay, but
then he says, even if the טלית Tallis *tallis* is exempt. Now
that's, what does that mean? All that we've been assuming since yesterday
is if the טלית Tallis *tallis* is exempt, like it's a nighttime
garment or like what we said today,
then it would be a שעטנז Shatnez *shatnez* problem. It only gets
out of שעטנז Shatnez *shatnez* because you're doing the מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*
of ציצית Tzitzis. *tzitzis* and because the garment is obligated. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, מאי טלית Tallis פטורה *Mai tallis peturah*? What
do you mean an exempt garment? אילימא דלית ביה שיעורא *Ileima d'leis
bei shiura*, it's not big enough yet to be obligated in ציצית
Tzitzis *tzitzis*, and it's nevertheless, you know, or it's not big enough
period to be obligated in ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzis*? והתניא בברייתא *V'hatanya b'braisa*,
טלית tallit שקטן מתכסה בה ראשו ורובו *tallis she'katan miskaseh bah rosho
v'rubo*? What is the minimum size of a garment to be obligated
in ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzis*? It has to be big enough that a
minor, you know, a young kid, we could use it to cover
the majority of his body, his head and his body, because you
know they would do it like an עטיפת הראש *atifas harosh*, like
you see some people put the טלית tallit *tallis* over their head.
They would sort of wrap it like, you know, like sometimes they
have in these Muslim countries, right, something that goes over the head
and then drapes down on the body. So if that is the
majority of the body for a minor, והגדול יוצא Yotzei, בה דרך
עראי *v'hagadol yotzei bah derech arai*, and an adult would use it
as a, you know, let's say to run out to the store,
it wouldn't be respectable to wear this as a full-size garment for
an adult, but he could at least use it as a, you
know, if he needed it for a quick need, so in that
case חייבת בציצית *chayaves b'tzitzis*, it's obligated. אין הקטן מתכסה בה ראשו
ורובו *Ein hakatan miskaseh bah rosho v'rubo*, but if it's not big
enough for a minor, אף על פי שהגדול יוצא בה עראי פטורה
*af al pi shehagadol yotzei bah arai peturah*, even if an adult
would use it to run out into the street with, okay, it's
still exempt. וכן לעניין כלאים *V'chein l'inyan kilayim*, that's just telling you
what the שיעור shiur *shiur* is, וכן לעניין כלאים *v'chein l'inyan kilayim*,
but then this ברייתא braita *braisa* ends by saying and the same
is true when it comes to שעטנז sha'atnez *shatnez*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, ואבינא בה *V'avina bah*, and we asked on this
ברייתא brayta *braisa*, מאי וכן לעניין כלאים *Mai v'chein l'inyan kilayim*? What
does that mean the same thing when it comes to שעטנז *shatnez*?
אילימא וכן לעניין איסור דכלאים *Ileima v'chein l'inyan issur d'kilayim*, that you
don't transgress the prohibition of שעטנז *shatnez* unless you're wearing a garment
that has wool and linen and the garment is a minimum size?
So that can't be true. והנן תנן *V'anan tenan*, אין עראי בכלאים
*ein arai b'kilayim*. When it comes to כלאים *kilayim*, the fact that
a garment is only used as a temporary garment is insignificant, and
there's no minimum size, okay, for garment in terms of the איסור
*issur* of שעטנז *shatnez*. So for what relevance are they saying that
this minimum size is relevant for שעטנז *shatnez*? ואמר רב Rav נחמן
בר יצחק *V'amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*, וכן לעניין סדין בציצית *v'chein
l'inyan sadin b'tzitzis*. What we mean is regarding שעטנז *shatnez* for ציצית
Tzitzis *tzitzis*. If this is a linen garment, if it's the size
that's obligated in ציצית Tzitzis, *tzitzis* and you're putting in the wool
תכלת tchelet *techeiles*, you're not transgressing שעטנז *shatnez*. But if it's not
the minimum size and you're putting in the wool תכלת tchelet *techeiles*,
you are being transgressing שעטנז *shatnez*. So you see that when the
garment is not obligated and you have and you're nevertheless using wool
with a linen ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzis* with a linen garment, it is
a violation of שעטנז *shatnez*. So and that's everything we've been assuming
since yesterday. So what does שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* mean when he says
there's no שעטנז *shatnez* problem even in an exempt טלית tallit *tallis*?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא מאי Ela mai? פטורה *Ella
mai peturah*? What is an exempt טלית tallit *tallis* mean? הטיחה למוטלת
*Hitiha l'muteles*. What we said before, that you added it to an
existing garment that already had ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzis* on it, okay? And
therefore, you know, if since the garment presumably is, since the garment
is obligated and then, you know, and presumably it already is שעטנז
*shatnez* because you already have in the original ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzis* on
there you've got the wool strands. So adding in another additional, you
know, ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzis*, the fifth ציצית Tzitzis. *tzitzis* on it, doesn't
make it more שעטנז *shatnez*. It's שעטנז שעטנז *shatnez shatnez*. Adding some
more wool doesn't make it more שעטנז *shatnez*. It's already a garment
that's obligated in ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzis* and you continue to do the
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* even when you add the extra sort of ציצית
Tzitzis *tzitzis*, the fifth ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzis* on it. So of course,
you know, there's no concern of שעטנז *shatnez*. So that's what it
means. So if that's true, והאמר רבי זירא חדא זימנא *V'ha'amar Rebbe
Zeira chada zimna*, didn't רבי זירא *Rebbe Zeira* already implicitly say that
when you add a fifth ציצית tzitzit, *tzitzis* to the thing, you
know, it's כשר Kosher? *kosher* and you can cut off what was
originally there and it's not a תעשה ולא מן העשוי Ta'aseh Velo
Min He'asui *ta'aseh v'lo min ha'asui* problem for whatever reason, you know,
which we didn't like fully, you know, explain in a fully satisfactory
way, but whatever it is, okay? So once that's true, the extra
ציצית tzitzit *tzitzis* will be valid if you cut off the original,
the original ציצית tzitzit? *tzitzis* were valid, the garment... The garment is
obligated in ציצית, tzitzit you're still doing the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית,
tzitzit so obviously there's no שעטנז problem. So why, if based on
the earlier teaching of רב זירא, Rav Zeira, we didn't need this
additional teaching of his that there's no שעטנז problem once he told
me that it's כשר? Kosher
So the גמרא Gemara says חדא מכלל דחברתה. Chada miklal dechaverta. Fine,
he didn't say both. He said one of them and the other
was inferred and derived from the other. Presumably the one that he
said was the more explicit, היא תלויה ומתלא, Hi telumutela, that if
you add an extra thing, it's כשר Kosher and it's going to
be כשר even the new thing you added if you cut off
the original ציצית. tzitzit. And once that's true and the whole thing
is obligated and you're יוצא, then we can infer that there's no
שעטנז problem. Okay, but there's a debate רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafot which
one did he say and which one did we infer. All right,
now the גמרא Gemara moves on. So that's sort of the end
of the תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta'aseh v'lo min he'asuy, and the
שעטנז in ציצית tzitzit בית הלל Beis Hillel בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
I mean not the total end but at least a pause in
that. תנו רבנן, Tano rabbanan, our Rabbis taught about 10 lines from
the top מ"א ע"א. Mem Aleph Amud Aleph. Our Rabbis taught. טלית
כפולה חייבת בציצית, Tallis kefulah chayaves betzitzis, רבי שמעון פוטר. Rabbi Shimon
poter. If you have a we dealt with this before, you have
a טלית tallit that is double length let's say and you folded
it over then it is obligated in ציצית tzitzit, and presumably means
you put the ציצית tzitzit at what is the current edges of
it the way you're using it at the fold and not at
the natural edges. The way you folded it now defines the shape
of the garment and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts. Okay it's a
little funny why does he exempt? He exempts because he doesn't consider
the fold really to change the shape of the garment. Okay, but
then he should at least obligate you to put it at the
natural end not at the folded end. It's a little unclear maybe
because like נישט אהין נישט אהער. Nishtehi nishteher. The way you use
it it should be at the folded end, the way it actually
is it should be at the natural end and
therefore since no
end edge is the clear edge it's exempt, seems to be the
point. Okay ושוין Veshovin but they agreed שאם כפלה ותפרה שחייבת. She'im
keflah veteferah shechayaves. If you not only folded it but you sewed
it up, now you really did shape the side change the shape
then you're obligated at the place of the fold. So the גמרא
Gemara, says תפרה פשיטא, Teferah peshita, if you sewed it of course
you've changed the garment. I mean any garment is done by folding
and sewing and so on. So the גמרא Gemara says no לא
צריכא דנקטה בכיסי. Lo tzericha denaketah bekesise. No, what we needed it
for is that you didn't actually sew it but you had bobby
pins to hold it in place. Okay but even so even though
it's a more temporary that is still enough to change the shape
of the garment and to say you put it at the fold.
רבה בר הונא איקלע לבי רבא Rabba bar Huna itkelei levei Rava
בר רב נחמן bar Rav Nachman חזייה דהוה מיכסי טלית כפולה Chazyei
dehavei michassei tallis kefulah and he saw that he was wearing a
folded טלית without the sewn up or the bobby pins ורמי ליה
חוטי עלוי כפליה Verami lei chutei iluyei kefeleh and the ציצית tzitzit.
were at the fold, the current shape of the garment. Then פשטה
Ifshatah and so imagine that like the two edges maybe were like
going down on both sides of his garment it was like a
tunic or something both sides of his body front and back they
were both like the hems of the
garment and then פשטה Ifshatah then he unfolded it and now he's
wearing the garment
ואתו חוטי וקמו להדי רישיה. V'ata chutei vekam lehadyei reishyei. So now
if the garment is now front and back then the place where
the original fold was is like right at his neck and therefore
but that's where he had the ציצית, tzitzis? the ציצית tzitzis. weren't
at the hem, the ציצית tzitzit? were now at his shoulders at
the neck because he had put them where the fold was because
he originally was wearing it folded. אמר ליה לאו היינו כנף דכתב
רחמנא. Amar lei lav hainu kanaf dechasav rachmana. So רבה בר הונא
Rabba bar Huna said to רבא בר רב נחמן Rava bar Rav
Nachman that's not the edge that the תורה Torah was talking about
you have it now on the middle not at the
edge דאורייתא De'oraisa that the תורה Torah that God wrote in the
תורה. Torah. אתא שדייה Ata shadyei so he threw it off איכסי
גלימא אחריתי Achasei glima achrisei and he put on a new garment.
You're right I'm not being יוצא ציצית Yotzei Tzitzis now so then
he put on a different garment that wouldn't have a fold or
whatever that had the ציצית tzitzit. in the right place. אמר ליה
Amar lei so רבא בר רב נחמן Rava bar Rav Nachman so
רבה בר הונא Rabba bar Huna still said to him you're not
done. מי סברת חובת גברא הוא חובת טלית הוא. Mi savras chovas
gavra hu chovas tallis hu. So this is a very important question
by ציצית tzitzit right the תורה Torah doesn't say you must wear
a garment with ציצית. tzitzit It says you must put ציצית tzitzit,
on your garments. So the question is how do you conceptualize that
is it that every garment that I own that has four corners
must have ציצית Tzitzit on them whether I'm wearing it or not
or is it when I wear it because it says אשר תכסה
בה Asher techaseh bo so is that just describing the type of
the garment or is it no when I wear it I must
ensure that there are ציצית Tzitzis, on it. So it's not the
חובת גברא Chovas gavra the personal obligation that I must Okay, but
is it that fundamentally all the garments have to have ציצית, Tzitzit
like your house has to have a מזוזה, mezuzah, or is it
when you wear it, then you're obligated to put ציצית Tzitzit. on
it or to ensure that there are ציצית? tzitzit So he says
it's an obligation of the garment and therefore I don't care that
you took it off.
You still have to fix it. You have a four corner garment
that does not have the ציצית tzitzit. in the right place. מי
סברת חובת גברא הוא, mi savras chovat gavra hu,
what makes you think that it's an obligation on the person and
dependent on whether you're wearing it or not, חובת טלית הוא. chovat
talis hu. It's an obligation on the garment that you own whether
you're wearing it or not. זיל רמי ליה, zil rami lei, go
put ציצית tzitzit on it. Okay, so now we're going to discuss
this issue of חובת גברא chovat gavra versus חובת מנא. chovat mana.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: לימא מסייע ליה, leima mesaye
lei, let me try to bring a support to you what we
spoke said before. חסידים הראשונים כיון שארגו בה שלוש היו מטילין בה
תכלת. chassidim harishonim keivan she'argu ba shalosh hayu matilin bah techeiles. So
the original righteous people as soon as they got to three finger
breadths whether the first three, the last three, that's when they would
put on the ציצית. tzitzit So that seems to indicate it was
important to them that as soon as it became a garment it
would have the ציצית tzitzit on it, right? And if the whole
obligation was only when you wore it, right, you understand, like if
it's like you have to have all your garments have to have
ציצית, tzitzit they were like, oh my God, before it becomes a
garment let's get the ציצית tzitzit on so there's not even a
second you know that that passes once it becomes a garment without
the ציצית. tzitzit So you could understand that. But if the whole
obligation only begins when you're wearing it, why did they go to
such extremes? Okay, good question.
So the גמרא Gemara says: no, שאני חסידים דמחמירי אנפשייהו. shani chassidim
d'machmiri a'nafshaihu. No, you know, they're very pious people, who knows, they
could be so stringent that even if they're only obligated when you
wear it, they wanted to put it on at the first opportunity.
ופליגי, u'pligi, now this idea that it's an obligation חובת מנא chovat
mana on the garment and doesn't focus on the person argues דמלאכא
d'malacha on the angel. What does that mean? דמלאכא אשכחיה לרב קטינא,
de'malacha ashkachlei l'Rav Katina, famous story, an angel found רב קטינא Rav
Katina דמיכסי סדינא d'michasei sadina that he was wearing a linen garment.
אמר ליה amar lei and he said to him: קטינא קטינא סדינא
בקיטא, Katina Katina sadina b'kayta, almost like rhymes. קטינא קטינא Katina Katina
that was his name. If you wear linen in the summer וסרבלא
בסיתוא v'sarv'la b'sitva and you wear like a cloak a heavy woolen
cloak in the fall or in the winter and רש"י Rashi says
that would be a type of a cloak that does not have
four corners,
ציצית מה תהא עליה, tzitzis ma tehei aleha, what's going to be
with the מצוה mitzvah ציצית? tzitzit, You're not obligated in the summer
because it's linen, you're not doing it in the winter because you
don't have four corners, you never do the מצוה mitzvah ציצית. tzitzit
Now before we get to the answer here or what the point
of the גמרא, Gemara what does it mean you're not doing the
מצוה mitzvah ציצית? tzitzit, If you have a linen garment, fine, don't
put the תכלת tchelet in, but at least put in the white,
the wool strings. So that's why as you'll see our גירסא girsa
is, you know, it's ציצית של תכלת מה
תהא עליה, tzitzis shel techeiles ma tehei aleha, which but that seems
to definitely be a gloss, but it's trying to answer that question
and saying like you're never fully doing the מצוה mitzvah. of ציצית.
tzitzit You don't do it in the winter because it's not four
cornered and you don't fully do it in the summer because you
don't put תכלת tchelet in it. Anyway תוספות Tosafos claims, says no,
the real גירסא girsa is just ציצית מה תהא עליה tzitzis ma
tehei aleh and for תוספות Tosafos it's an evidence that when you
have a linen garment the תקנה takkana of the רבנן Rabbis because
they were afraid of שעטנז was not to put ציצית tzitzit. in
it at all. Okay, so anyway, so that's interest for that discussion
we had yesterday. Anyway the גמרא Gemara is saying since the angel
was giving him a hard time, right, if the whole obligation had
nothing to do with when I'm wearing it, the whole obligation was
focused on what's in my drawer, you know when you go to
my house what's in my closet, then I could totally be doing
the מצוה Mitzvah, of all the garments in my closet, whether I'm
wearing or not is irrelevant to the מצוה. Mitzvah This critique only
makes sense if the obligation is dependent on him wearing it. And
then he's saying you are never putting yourself in a situation where
you have this obligation of ציצית tzitzit because, you know, you never
wear such a garment. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה, amar lei, so anyway רב קטינא
Rav Katina said back to the angel: ענישת אעשה, anishat a'asei, am
I being punished for not doing a מצות עשה? mitzvas asei? Now
תוספות Tosafos says of course, you know, I mean even the בית
דין Beis Din would force people to take לולב, lulav, sit in
a סוכה sukkah if somebody was refusing, but it means I'm not
violating an עשה, asei, nobody says I had an obligation to put
on a four corner garment to be obligated in ציצית, tzitzit I'm
just not putting myself in a circumstance where I have to do
the where I have to do it. You're going to give me
a hard time for that? It's sort of like somebody who like
never eats bread so they don't have to do. They're not violating
anything, but they're sort of avoiding the מצוה, Mitzvah avoiding it. So
he says, I'm going to get punished for that? אמר ליה, Amar
Lei, so he said back to him, בעידן דאיכא
רתחא Idan de-ika ritcha ענשינן. anshinan. Yes, when God gets angry, maybe
as a standard, you're not doing anything wrong, but if it's a
time of God's anger, then the fact that look, you're trying to
avoid מצוות Mitzvos is something that you will have to pay for.
Okay. Now, אי אמרת בשלמא, Im amart bishlama, now that was the
story. Now the גמרא Gemara, is going to bring it into its
discussion. אי אמרת בשלמא חובת גברא הוא, Im amart bishlama chovas gavra
hu, if it is an obligation that is dependent on wearing it,
היינו דמחיוב דלא כרמי, Hainu de-michaivei de-lo karmei, that's why he's getting
held accountable because he did not put it on and he didn't
put on the
ציצית tzitzit because he didn't create the circumstances of being obligated. אלא
אי אמרת חובת טלית הוא, Ela im amart chovas talis hu, הא
לא מחייב, Halo michaive, but if it's about, has nothing to do
with wearing it or not, it's just when you have garments in
your closet, you have to make sure that they have the ציצית,
tzitzit so he never had the obligation, meaning he never owned those
garments. Right? It's a little different between sort of saying like, look,
I just don't happen—like if somebody doesn't own a house. Just doesn't
happen to own a house. You don't give them a hard time
saying, "Oh, you're not doing the מצוה mitzvah of מזוזה, Mezuzah, you
have to go ahead and buy a house to do a מצוה
of מזוזה." Mezuzah. Okay, he didn't own four-cornered garments, no obligation. All
right, but when we focus on when you wear it you then
you are obligated, then there's more sort of focusing on are you
doing, how are you acting, and are you acting in a way
that is avoiding the obligation or is it obligating you. It's less
about the static reality of do you own these garments and more
about the actions that you're doing. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
this really makes much more sense if the focus is on the
sense of the
obligation on the person when you're wearing it and not just the
status or the static reality of having them in the garments on
your closet. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says,
אלא Ela מאי? But the גמרא Gemara says no, that was a
little tortured what I was just saying. חובת גברא הוא? Chovas gavra
hu? I don't get it, says the גמרא, Gemara even if you
say it's about when you're wearing it,
נהי דחייבי רחמנא כי מכסי טלית דבת חיובא, Nihideichivei rachmana ki michasei
talis de-bar chiyuva, fine, it's a personal obligation, but not a personal
obligation to make sure to put on such a garment. What the
תורה Torah obligates you when you wear a garment that is obligated.
כי מכסי טלית דלאו בת חיובא הוא, Ki michasei talis de-lav bar
chiyuva hu, מי חייבי רחמנא? Mi chivei rachmana? But when you're wearing
a טלית that is not obligated, the תורה Torah isn't obligating you.
So even if it's a personal obligation, the גמרא Gemara says there's
not really a difference. If you say you don't own four-cornered garments,
you don't have ציצית tzitzit on them, the angel wouldn't give you
a hard time. So you should say in the same vein: you're
not wearing four-cornered garments, the angel should not give you a hard
time. Who cares whether it's about in your closet or wearing them?
Either way, they're not the circumstances of obligation. So why are you
being given a hard time? So גמרא Gemara says, אלא what you
must say is, הכי קאמר ליה, Hachi kama lei, this is what
he's saying to him: טצדקי למפתר נפשך מציצית? Taztaki le-miftar nafshach mi-tzitzis?
Which is sort of what we were saying before. Fine, you're not
directly violating, you're not getting out of an obligation, but you're doing
schemes in order to avoid being obligated. And that's why he was
being held accountable. You're right, whether it's a חובת גברא Chovas gavra
or it's a חובת מנא, Chovas mana, you didn't violate anything. He
never had the circumstances, but he was given a hard time for
avoiding being obligated. Now the question is, does that still mean that
there's an emphasis on once the גמרא Gemara gives that answer, does
it still think it works better in the context of חובת גברא
Chovas gavra for the reason I was saying? It's one thing to
say scheming when it's focusing on what are you wearing, that's more
of being holding him account for scheming as opposed to that you
don't happen to own those garments. Or no? Or is it saying
either way?
Now we can't prove חובת גברא Chovas gavra or חובת מנא, Chovas
mana, the point is you're just avoiding obligation and it doesn't matter
which one, that's what you're being held accountable for. Okay, so that's
a little debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafos. All right. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, we're still going to continue
with this discussion of חובת גברא, Chovas gavra, חובת מנא. Chovas mana.
אמר רב
טיבי בר קיסנא אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Tivi bar Kisnai amar Shmuel,
so said רב טיבי בר קיסנא Rav Tivi bar Kisnai in the
name of שמואל, Shmuel כלי קופסא חייבין בציצית. Klei kufsa chiyavin be-tzitzis.
Garments in your dresser are obligated in ציצית. tzitzit Okay, it's very
clear the position of חובת מנא. Chovas mana. It's not about when
you're wearing them, as long as you own them you have to
have them. ומודה שמואל, U-modei Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel. agrees, בזקן שעשה
לכבודו שפטורה, Bezaken she-asa le-chvodo she-ptura, that if an older person made
it for his honor, which is a euphemism meaning to be shrouds,
then it's exempt. Why? Even though you're obligated just by owning it.
Because מאי טעמא, Mai taama, what's the reason? אשר תכסה בה אמר
רחמנא. Asher techase bah amar rachmana. אמר רחמנא amar Rachmana והאי לאו
לכסויי עבידא v'hai lav l'ichsu'ei avida it says that you cover yourself
with, cover yourself, and this isn't made to cover yourself with. Now,
it's a little funny, it is made to cover yourself, but cover
yourself when you're dead. But that's not the normal way meaning of
what it means to wear clothing, okay? And therefore, it is seen
as not the type of garment that is obligated. So yes, you're
obligated even if you're not wearing it, but shrouds are not, you
know, it's garments that you wear when you're alive, not garments that
you wear when you're dead.
So, the גמרא Gemara says like this, לאו לכסויי עבידא, lav l'ichsu'ei
avida, האי
לאו לכסויי עבידא. v'hai lav l'ichsu'ei avida. בהיא שעתא, b'hi sha'ata, however,
at that time when you actually now put the shroud on, the
person is actually dead, okay, בהיא שעתא, b'hi sha'ata, ודאי רמינן ביה.
vadai raminan beih. Then we actually put ציצית tzitzit on the shroud
if it has four corners. We obviously don't do that. מאי טעמא?
mai ta'ama? משום לועג לרש חרף עושהו. mishum lo'eg larash chereif osehu.
If you a person who mocks a poor person blasphemes God. Who's
the poor person here? The dead person is poor because they are
poor of מצוות. mitzvot. They're now in a world where they cannot
do מצוות. mitzvot. And when you so in that time, you don't
want to say we're sending this person off to his, you know,
final resting place wearing a four-cornered garment without ציצית. tzitzit It's almost
like mocking him. Ha, look, he's dead! Because he's dead, he's wearing
a garment and he doesn't have to put ציצית tzitzit on him.
So because we don't want to be mocking the fact that he's
no longer obligated in מצוות, mitzvot, we do put ציצית tzitzit, on.
So it's a little ironic, right? You don't put ציצית tzitzit on
when you're alive because it's only made for when you're dead, and
when you're dead is when the ציצית tzitzit are on. But the
ציצית tzitzit are on when you're dead not because it's an obligation,
but because of we don't want to mock him. Now, תוספות Tosafot
actually points out that the practice in אשכנז Ashkenaz was the reverse.
The practice in אשכנז Ashkenaz was to actually rip the ציצית tzitzit?
off of a טלית that they would cover the person with, a
טלית that the person wore when they were alive and had ציצית,
tzitzit and to tear them off before putting him in the ground.
So that's quite fascinating, probably an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael מנהג minhag
that went to אשכנז Ashkenaz as opposed to this which is a
בבל Bavel מנהג. minhag. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אמר רחבא אמר רב יהודה, amar Rachava amar Rav Yehuda, טלית שנקראה
חוץ לשלוש יתפור תוך שלוש לא יתפור. tallit shenikra'a chutz l'shalosh yitfor
toch shalosh lo yitfor. If a garment was torn outside of three
you can sew it up, within three you can't sew it up.
So I'm going to explain this like תוספות Tosafot not like רש״י.
Rashi. The way תוספות Tosafot explains it means like this, you know,
if it tore with the ציצית tzitzit on the corner, okay, and
it tore off, and it tore off and it was from the
garment with the ציצית, tzitzit, but it was within three handbreadths of
the edge. Then in that case, okay, that's like the ציצית tzitzit
were taken off the garment and if you sew it back on,
it's תעשה ולא מן העשוי, ta'aseh v'lo min he'asuy cause you're sewing
on a corner and then poof, magically you have ציצית. Tzitzit. You
didn't actually put the ציצית Tzitzit. on, you put the corner on
and the ציצית Tzitzit were already there. That's תוך שלוש, toch shalosh,
don't sew it up. חוץ לשלוש, chutz l'shalosh, if it tore more
than three fingerbreadths into the garment, so then and the whole thing
tore off, so now you have this corner with ציצית tzitzit, but
it's a larger piece of the garment. And because it is three
fingerbreadth, it's already significant to have the status to some degree of
a garment. So in that case, it's seen as if it still
is, you know, somehow because it's significant and therefore the ציצית tzitzit,
on it can be seen as still on a garment. When you
go back and sew it back up, you're just restoring what was,
you know, you are not actually, you know, you're taking a garment
and it's still an extension of the other garment and you're just
combining them again and it's not תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta'aseh v'lo
min he'asuy. problem. Okay, so that's the teaching here.
תניא נמי הכי tanya nami hachi ובלבד של צמרא ליה u'v'bilvad shel
tzimra lei טלית שנקראה חוץ לשלוש יתפור תוך שלוש רבי מאיר אומר
לא יתפור, tallit shenikra'a chutz l'shalosh yitfor toch shalosh Rabbi Meir omer
lo yitfor, וחכמים אומרים יתפור. v'Chachamim omrim yitfor. And the חכמים Chachamim
actually allow you to sew it on, which is fascinating, which would
seem that they're not bothered with תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta'aseh v'lo
min he'asuy. Maybe they consider that to be an עשייה, asiya, sewing
on this, you know, cloth with the ציצית tzitzit is like putting
ציצית tzitzit on.
ושוין, v'shavin, but they agree, שלא יביא אפילו אמה על אמה ממקום
אחר ובתכלת ותולה בה. shelo yavi afilu ama al ama mimakom acher
u'v'techeilet v'toleh bah. Okay,
when can you restore sew it back with the ציצית tzitzit on?
That's when you're restoring it and then you're just making it whole
again. But if you, let's say, tore half of a טלית off,
a big piece from טלית A, and now you want to sew
that edge with the two corners on it to, you know, the
edge of טלית B, that you can't do. That we don't say
is like, oh, now it works. No, now it's תעשה ולא מן
העשוי. ta'aseh v'lo min he'asuy So even if it's a big garment
with a ציצית tzitzit on, that doesn't give you the right to
now combine it with another one. That's a תעשה ולא מן העשוי
problem. And it only worked when it was the same garment and
you were restoring it.
Okay, ובתכלת ותולה בה, u'v'techeilet v'toleh bah, ושוין שמביא תכלת ממקום אחר
ותולה בה. v'shavin shemeivi techeilet mimakom acher v'toleh bah. But they do
agree that you can take ציצית tzitzit *tzitzis*, the ציצית tzitzit *tzitzis*
themselves off of טלית *tallis* A and put it on טלית *tallis*
B. Not the piece of the garment, but the actual ציצית tzitzit
*tzitzis*. Top of מ''א ע''ב *mem alef amud beis*. ובלבד שלא תהא
מופסקת *u'v'levad shelo tehei mufseket*, provided that it that they are not
torn. רש''י *Rashi* said that means that all of the strings are
still there. You know, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says like it seems a
little strange what the point is of saying that. But okay. שמע
מינה *shma mina* anyway, the point is the גמרא *Gemara* says you
can transfer the string, the ציצית tzitzit. *tzitzis*. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says שמע מינה *shma mina*, we hear from this, מתירין מבגד לבגד
matirin mibeged l'beged *matirin mi'beged le'beged*, that you're allowed to remove ציצית
tzitzit *tzitzis* from garment A and put them on garment B. Okay,
why might you not be allowed to do it? Well, because, you
know, A you're you're taking the מצוה *mitzvah* away from A. Especially
if you think that ציצית *tzitzis* are חובת מנא *chovas mana*. If
they're חובת מנא *chovas mana*, then all your garments are obligated. So
how can you take this garment away, you know, remove the מצוה
*mitzvah* that this garment is still obligated in, you know, this and
you know and to put it on a different one? Okay, but
nevertheless, this sounds like it's okay. Why? Maybe because it's חובת גברא
*chovas gavra*. So if it's חובת גברא *chovas gavra*, it's no big
deal. I'm going to put it on the one I'm going to
wear. It doesn't matter that the other one doesn't have it. I
don't have an obligation to make sure the other one has it
if I'm not wearing it. Okay, and maybe even if the other
one actually already is, even if you say חובת מנא *chovas mana*,
maybe there still would be a I I still should prefer to
have the ציצית *tzitzis* on the one I'm going to wear rather
than on the one I'm not going to wear. So the גמרא
*Gemara* doesn't exactly tie it into the חובת מנא חובת גברא *chovas
mana chovas gavra*. It might be very aligned, but there's ways to
make it that different positions that people take on this question of
can you remove ציצית *tzitzis* from one garment and put it on
the other could work according to either approach of חובת גברא חובת
מנא *chovas gavra chovas mana*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says שמע מינה
מתירין מבגד לבגד shma mina matirin mibeged l'beged. *shma mina matirin mi'beged
le'beged*. So we infer from this that you can remove from garment
A and put on garment B. גמרא *Gemara* says, not necessarily, דילמא
דאיבלי *dilma de'ivli*. Maybe it means if garment A wore out and
is no longer usable. Now you can salvage the ציצית *tzitzis* and
untie them from A and put them on B. But it's not
clear though you can take them off of A if A is
still a usable garment. תנו רבנן Tana Rabbanan, *tanu rabanan*. Okay, so
we're going to double back to this case in a little bit
about מתירין מבגד לבגד *matirin mi'beged le'beged*, but first
a different point. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan, טלית שכולה תכלת tchelet, *tanu
rabanan tallis she'kulah techeiles*. Going back to the blue, the blue טלית
*tallis*. כל מיני צבעונין פוטרין בה חוץ מקלא אילן *kol minei tivonin
potrin bah chutz mi'kala ilan*. All you can use all colors for
the white of the of it, right? Because we've had this way
at the beginning of the פרק *perek*. That since it says that
you should put על ציצית הכנף פתיל תכלת tchelet *al tzitzis hakanaf
psil techeiles*, the תכלת tchelet, *techeiles* goes on the ציצית *tzitzis* that
are already there. So normally the כנף *kanaf* means כנף *kanaf* and
presumably that means the same material, the same color of the corner.
There's a whole question how significant color is, but this seems to
say it is.
Nevertheless, even if the garment when the garment is all blue, you
have to have the first ציצית *tzitzis* that precede the תכלת tchelet,
*techeiles* or, you know, that conceptually precede the תכלת tchelet, *techeiles*, the
ציצית *tzitzis* of the כנף *kanaf*, it has to be different from
the פתיל תכלת *psil techeiles*. So it has to be a different
color. So you can use any color, כל מיני צבעונין פוטרים אותה
*kol minei tivonin potrim osah* okay, בה *bah*, חוץ מקלא אילן *chutz
mi'kala ilan*. But you can't use קלא אילן Kala Ilan. *kala ilan*
because קלא אילן Kala Ilan. *kala ilan*, which is basically like indigo,
is the exact same color. It's not כשר *kosher* for תכלת *techeiles*,
but it's the same color as תכלת *techeiles*. So what this is
basically saying is, in a normal garment, we'll see in a minute,
let's say it's red, let's say it's yellow, the ציצית *tzitzis* are
supposed to be the same color. Red or yellow, maybe also white
would be good. Okay, there's some question about other colors, but for
now we'll assume white or the color of the garment itself. But
when it is a blue garment, it has to be something different
from the color of the garment itself and at that point it
doesn't matter what color it is. Do whatever color you want. Because
since it can't be the color of the garment itself, you're free
to do whatever color you want. Okay, but not blue, not קלא
אילן Kala Ilan, *kala ilan*. מיתיבי *meisivei*, says the גמרא *Gemara*, I'll
ask you on this. טלית אין פוטר בה אלא מינה *tallis ein
poter bah ela minah*. Okay, we the ברייתא Baraisa *braisa* teaches the
only thing you can for טלית *tallis* you can only use for
the white strings, the non-תכלת *non-techeiles* strings, the same type of strings
as the garment itself. Either that means material or it means color
or both. טלית שכולה תכלת *tallis she'kulah techeiles*, what if it's all
blue? מביא תכלת ודבר אחר *meivi techeiles v'davar acher* you bring תכלת
*techeiles* and some other string ותולה בה *v'toleh bah* and you put
it on it. וקלא אילן לא יביא *v'kala ilan lo yavi* but
the other color so that's so far consistent. Some other color that
isn't blue, any other color, now we're still consistent. But then it
says like this, don't use קלא אילן Kala Ilan *kala ilan*, וקלא
אילן לא יביא *v'kala ilan lo yavi*, this indigo, ואם הביא כשר
*v'im heivi kasher*. But if you did, it's כשר *kosher*. So it's
it's very close to what we taught except the issue of בדיעבד
b'di'eved *b'di'eved*. This is saying בדיעבד b'di'eved *b'di'eved* it's כשר *kosher* and
before you said בדיעבד b'di'eved *b'di'eved* it was. invalid. So אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, if you use קלא
אילן. Kala Ilan, So אמר רב Rav? נחמן בר יצחק, לא קשיא,
lo kashya, הא דטיפלא, ha d'tifla, כאן בטלית בת ארבע חוטין, kan
b'talit bat arba chutin, כאן בטלית בת שמונה חוטין. kan b'talit bat
shmoneh chutin. Okay? It depends whether there are four strings or eight
strings. So this is very confusing exactly what it means, but the
way רש״י Rashi explains it is that is that
the case where it says בדיעבד it's kosher is that you already
had the four strings that make up you know the ציצית at
a given corner and those four strings were done correctly it was
the תכלת and some other color. And now you want to add
another four strings of קלא אילן. Kala Ilan, That you shouldn't do
לכתחילה l'chatchila because I mean first of all there's a whole בל
תוסיף bal tosif question which whatever is you know we're not going
to get into. And don't do it לכתחילה l'chatchila also because as
we'll see you might think that they wind up thinking they're really
תכלת and cut them off of this garment since they're extra and
wind up using them on another garment. So that's why you shouldn't
do it לכתחילה l'chatchila but בדיעבד it's kosher because you did the
first four strings correctly. So that's what it says when it says
כאן בטלית בת ארבע חוטין kan b'talit bat arba chutin when it
says it's not kosher is if you only have the four strings
and you do two of תכלת and two of קלא אילן, Kala
Ilan, that's not valid because you don't have a different color. כאן
בטלית בת שמונה חוטין kan b'talit bat shmoneh chutin when it says
don't do קלא אילן Kala Ilan, but if you do it's kosher,
that's when you have the original four strings the right way, two
of תכלת and two of some other color that is not blue,
not תכלת, not קלא אילן, Kala Ilan and you add four more
of קלא אילן, Kala Ilan two of תכלת excuse me and two
of some other color that is not blue, not תכלת, not קלא
אילן, Kala Ilan. and you add four more of קלא אילן, and
that you shouldn't do but בדיעבד it will be okay don't because
you have the four basic ones right. And the reason not to
do it is you might come to transfer those strings elsewhere. Why
it's not בל תוסיף, bal tosif, תוספות Tosafot suggests that here we're
talking that all of those eight strings are part of the same
bundle, you know start of the same wrapping. בל תוסיף bal tosif
is when you have one wrapping of ציצית, you know one with
the strings with the wraps and the knots and whatever and then
another one like it you know of four strings in a separate
bundle. But here it would be of all of the eight together,
that might not be בל תוסיף. bal tosif. Okay anyway,
so the גמרא says now with this answer שמע מינה מתירין מבגד
לבגד. Since the reason not to do it is because you might
come and take those four of קלא אילן from the eight and
put them on another garment and think that they're תכלת, that shows
that you're allowed to remove from one garment to the next. Now
that's pretty funny because you're here you're removing from one garment but
you're not doing it to steal the מצוה away from the existing
garment. You're taking four but you're still leaving four behind. But let's
see what the גמרא says. דילמא דעבד. dilma d'avad. No, maybe you're
not allowed to but we don't want you to have these extra
קלא אילן things because you might do it anyway and then you'll
still think that that garment is okay and it's not okay the
new garment because it has it's not real תכלת, it's really קלא
אילן. Okay? It's strange the גמרא could have said that it's everybody
agrees it's okay to be מתיר matir when you have extra strings.
But anyway. איתמר Itmar was taught, now we're going to go back
and explicitly have that debate. רב אמר אין מתירין מבגד לבגד Rav
amar ein matirin mibeged l'beged you don't remove from one garment to
the next ושמואל אמר מתירין מבגד לבגד u'Shmuel amar matirin mibeged l'beged
you do. רב אמר Rav amar now and now we're going to
have a whole list of things of רב and שמואל and we're
joining them together because there's a consistent פסק. psak. רב אמר אין
מדליקין מנר לנר Rav amar ein madlikin miner l'ner you can't light
חנוכה Chanukah candles use one light to light the other ושמואל אמר
מדליקין מנר לנר u'Shmuel amar madlikin miner l'ner you can. רב אמר
אין הלכה כרבי שמעון בגרירה Rav amar ein halacha k'Rabbi Shimon b'grirah
we don't rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon when it comes to
dragging a bench in a or you know or chair in a
field on שבת Shabbat that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's not
a problem even though you might make a furrow you're not intending
and דבר שאינו מתכוין davar she'eino mitkavein is מותר. mutar. If you're
not intending and it won't definitely happen it's permissible. ושמואל אמר הלכה
כרבי שמעון בגרירה u'Shmuel amar halacha k'Rabbi Shimon b'grirah we rule like
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אמר אביי Amar Abaye says אביי Abaye כל
מילי דמר עביד כרב kol milei d'Mar avid k'Rav all of the
masters that the master like רבה Rabba did like רב לבר מהני
תלת דעביד כשמואל l'bar mehani tlat d'avid k'Shmuel there were three areas
that פסקן paskan like שמואל. מתירין מבגד לבגד number one you can
transfer ציצית from one garment to another ומדליקין מנר לנר u'madlikin miner
l'ner there's a nice parallel there right and you can light one
נר חנוכה ner Chanukah from the other you know that's the whole
question of do you really need a שמש. shamash. והלכה כרבי שמעון
בגרירה v'halacha k'Rabbi Shimon b'grirah right and we rule like רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon when it comes to גרירה grirah דתניא d'tanya we taught
in a ברייתא רבי שמעון אומר גורר אדם מיטה כסא וספסל ובלבד
שלא יתכוין לעשות חריץ. Rabbi Shimon omer gorer adam mita kisei v'safsal
u'bilvad shelo yitkavein la'asot charitz. You can drag a bed or a
chair you know in a field as long as you're not intending
to make a furrow and it won't definitely make a furrow that
is okay on שבת Shabbat it's דבר שאינו מתכוין. davar she'eino mitkavein.
All right new point, lot of stuff here. רב יהודה מסרי לקיצרי.
Rav Yehuda masrei l'katzrei. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda gave his ציצית you
know his garment with ציצית over to the dry cleaner or the
launderer and he wasn't afraid that it would ruin the strings. It
does happen sometimes. רב חנינא עבד ליה סיסי. Rav Chanina avid lei
sisei. רב חנינא Rav Chanina made like they bundled
them up like
you know like within the garment itself to protect them from the
wash. Very fascinating. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, nice little break from our
halachic discussions. כמה חוטים הוא נותן? Kama chutim hu noten? You know,
you would have thought this is like the very first question we
should have asked. How many strings make up the ציצית? בית
שמאי אומרים ארבע, Beit Shammai omrim arba, four, which is actually what
we do, okay, four folded over which becomes eight. בית הלל אומרים
גמל, Beit Hillel omrim gimel, only three. וכמה תהא משולשת? Ve-kama tehei
meshuleshet? Okay, and how, how much should it be, like have like
the string part compared to the bound up part, you know, the
wrapped and the knots? בית שמאי אומרים ארבע Beit Shammai omrim arba
ובית הלל אומרים גמל. u-Beit Hillel omrim gimel. So בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says four fingerbreadths, so תוספות says this means that the wrapped
up knot part is four fingerbreadths, and if you remember before we
said a third is the knots and two-thirds are the strings, so
then the entire length of the ציצית would be twelve fingerbreadths. Okay,
so so
the wrapped up part is four fingerbreadths. ובית
הלל אומרים גמל. U-Beit Hillel omrim gimel. No, the wrapped up part
is only three and then the remainder would be six. Okay. וגמל
שבית הלל אומרים, Ve-gimel she-Beit Hillel omrim, now the ברייתא teaches, those
three fingerbreadths, so how how do we measure them? גמל
שבית הלל אומרים אחת מארבע בטפח, Gimel she-Beit Hillel omrim achat me-arba
be-tefach, is one out of four that makes up a טפח. tefach.
Okay, so a טפח tefach is made up of four
fingerbreadths, but there's different ways of measuring טפחים tefachim and which types
of fingers are we talking about? So we're just being very clear
these are three standard finger widths assuming four finger widths to a
טפח. tefach. Okay. של כל אדם, Shel kol adam, of a normal
person. אמר פפא, Amar Papa, טפח דאורייתא, tefach de-oraita,
in terms of what is a טפח tefach from a Torah's perspective,
ארבע בגודל, arba be-godel, it would be four finger widths of your
thumb. שית בקטנה, shis be-ketana, or six finger widths if you were
using your pinky. חמש בתילתא, chamesh be-tilta, and five finger widths if
you're using your, you know, what do you call it, you know,
your your index finger. Okay, so and these are all the same
size, it just depends which finger you're measuring by. Fine. So when
we were saying four according to this it would have been four
thumb widths. When we're saying you know three fit, when בית הלל
Beit Hillel says three it means three out of four of a
טפח, tefach, so according to this that would mean three thumb widths.
אמר רב הונא ארבע בתוך ארבע ומשולשת ארבע. Amar Rav Huna: arba
betoch arba u-meshuleshet arba. So he says we rule basically like בית
שמאי Beit Shammai fascinating, four strings within four finger widths of the
edge of the garment, okay, that's we're going to discuss that how
close the ציצית should be to the edge of the garment, they
have to be within four finger widths and they and the the
wrapping and the knotted part is four finger widths and the and
the loose strings is double that is eight finger widths. רב יהודה
אומר גמל בתוך גמל משולשת גמל. Rav Yehuda omer gimel betoch gimel
meshuleshet gimel. No, three strings within three finger widths and the wrapped
up part is three fingers. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, said
רב פפא, Rav Papa, הלכתא, hilchesa, the ruling is, ארבע, arba, four
strings which we know that's our ציצית, בתוך שלוש, betoch shalosh, within
three finger widths, which is everything we've been talking about till now,
if you remember, it spoke about the garment tearing off within three
finger widths, outside of three finger widths. So the ציצית go within
the final three finger widths of the garment,
משולשת ארבע, meshuleshet arba, but yes I do agree that the wrapping
and the knotting part is four finger widths wide.
Okay. למימר, Lemeimar, says the Gemara, this seems to say דאית להו
שיעורא, de-is lehu shiura, that there's a, you know, שיעור shiur? of
how much of the strings have to come out, the ratio between
from the knotted part, how much the knotted part has to be,
how much the strings have to be. ורמינהו, U-reminhu, I'll ask you
on this: ציצית. So this is a דרשה drasha on the פסוק
pasuk ציצית. אין ציצית אלא יוצא. Ein tzitzit ela yotze. ציצית means
like the free strings, you know, like the locks of the hair
are called ציצית ראשו, tzitzit rosho, okay, the things that is coming
out of the knot. ואין ציצית אלא משהו, Ve-ein tzitzit ela mashehu,
and it's sufficient that it be even a tiny amount. וכבר עלו
זקני בית שמאי וזקני בית הלל לעליית יוחנן בן בתירה, Ve-kavar alu
ziknei Beit Shammai ve-ziknei Beit Hillel le-aliyat Yochanan ben Beteira, they the
elders went up to this attic, ואמרו ציצית אין לה שיעור, ve-amru:
tzitzit ein la shiur, there's no minimum amount. כיוצא בו לולב אין
בו שיעור, Ki-yotze bo lulav ein bo shiur, similarly there's no minimum
amount of a לולב. lulav. So what are we saying that, you
know, this part has to be four finger widths and all of
that, it says that there's no שיעור? shiur So the Gemara says
no: מאי לאו אין לה שיעור כלל? mai lav ein la shiur
klal? Although doesn't it mean there's no שיעור shiur at all? So
the Gemara says לאו, lav, no, that's not what it means. It
means אין לה שיעור למעלה, ein la shiur le-mala, there's no maximum
length, okay, אבל יש לה שיעור למטה, aval yesh la shiur le-mata,
there is a minimum, it's what we've been talking about, the minimum
four finger widths etc. etc. דאי לא תימא הכי, De-ila teima hachi,
because if you don't say that, כיוצא בו לולב אין לו שיעור,
ki-yotze bo lulav ein lo shiur, we said oh and also the
לולב lulav has no minimum, that's not true. הכא נמי דאין לו
שיעור כלל? Hacha nami de-ein lo shiur klal? Do you mean to
say there's really no minimum?
ודתנן, Ve-hatnan, but we learned: לולב שיש בו גמל טפחים כדי lulav
she-yesh bo gimel tfachim kedei So אלא אין לו שיעור למעלה ela
ein lo shiur l'ma'ala when it's talk— when it says there's no
שיעור shiur. amount by a לולב, lulav, it means there's no maximum
amount. אבל יש לו שיעור למטה, aval yesh lo shiur l'mata, there
is a minimum. So הכא נמי hacha nami also by the ציצית,
אין לו שיעור למעלה ein lo shiur l'ma'ala what בית הלל ובית
שמאי Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai were saying was, there's no maximum שיעור.
shiur. אבל יש לו שיעור למטה aval yesh lo shiur l'mata there
is a minimum שיעור. shiur Okay, now that's fine except the ברייתא
said אפילו משהו, afilu mashehu, even the tiniest amount. So רש״י Rashi
says what that means is if it got cut and you're left
with a tiny amount, גרדומין gardumim what we discussed earlier, that will
be okay. But the basic ruling of אין לו שיעור ein lo
shiur means no maximum and yes, there is at least a לכתחילה
l'chatkhila שיעור shiur of these four fingerbreadths and there is some minimum
שיעור that is required. Okay. תנו רבנן, our rabbis taught: ציצית, אין
ציצית אלא ענף. ein tzitzit ela anaf. ציצית means like, you know,
the free-flowing strings. וכן הוא אומר, vechen hu omer, and it also
says, ויקחני בציצית ראשי, vayikacheini betzitzit roshi, He took me by the
strands of my hair. So the גדיל gedil is the knotted part
and the wrappings, and the ציצית are the flowing strings. ואמר אביי,
v'amar Abaye, and אביי Abaye says, וצריך לפרודה כצוציתא דארמאי, v'tzarich lefroda
ke-tzutzita d'Armaye, and you have to like, you know, keep the strands
of your ציצית separate, you don't let them get all knotted up
to one another, the same like the non-Jewish like hair, you know,
style has, you know, you would separate out the hairs and keep
the hair flowing— maybe there would be a, you know, a braided
part and a free-flowing part. תנו רבנן, our rabbis taught: הטיל על
הקרן או על הגדיל כשירה. hittel al hakern o al hagedil kshira.
If you put the ציצית right at the corner or right at
like the edge of the garment, it's kosher. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
פוסל בשתיהן. Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov posel bishteihen. No, he says it's
invalid. They can't be right at the edge, right at the corner.
Okay. כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רב גידל אמר רב, keman azla ha
d'amar Rav Giddel amar Rav, who is this going like the teaching
of רב גידל Rav Giddel in the name of רב? ציצית צריכה
שתהא נוטפת על הקרן. tzitzit tzericha shetehei notefet al hakern. The ציצית
have to be like, like dropping from the corner. Not at the
edge, but as we know the hole of the ציצית is a
few inches in at both sides and it like drops down, and
maybe it also goes to the side of the— not to the
bottom edge, according to the standard interpretation it goes to the side
edge and then it like drops down from the side, but either
way it's dropping down and it's not right at the edge. Okay.
שנאמר, shenemar, as it says, על כנפי בגדיהם, al kanfei bigdeihem, on
the corners of their garment. I'm not exactly sure how that means
dropping. כמאן, keman, who is that going like? כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב,
ke'Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov, like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rebbe Eliezer ben
Yaakov that says you don't put it exactly at the edge. And
as we saw— fine. So אמר רב יעקב אמר רב יוחנן,
amar Rav
Yaakov amar Rav Yochanan, וצריך שירחיק מלא קשר גודל. v'tzarich sheyarchik melo
kesher godel. How far does it have to be from the edge?
The, you know, the what's it called, the knuckle, you know, from
your finger, from the knuckle to the top of your thumb, you
know, the joint, that's the width it has to be from the
edge, from both edges.
ואיצטריך דרב פפא ואיצטריך דרב יעקב. v'itztarich d'Rav Pappa v'itztarich d'Rav Yaakov.
You need רב פפא׳ס Rav Pappa's teaching, that of— that the ציצית
have to be within three fingerbreadths. Remember that's what we were talking,
three fingerbreadths or four fingerbreadths? And you need רב יעקב Rav Yaakov
that says that it has to be a knuckle like, you know,
a joint— thumb joint width away from the edge. Because one is
a minimum and one is a maximum is why you need both,
which is what the גמרא is going to say.
דאי מהא דרב פפא, de'ei me'ha d'Rav Pappa, had it just been
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, הוה אמינא תוך ג׳ דלא לירחק טפי, hava
amina tokh gimmel d'lo lirchak tfei, you know, he says it has
to be within three, that's the maximum distance it can be from
the edge, don't make it any more distant. וכמה דמקרב מעלי, vekhama
d'mekarev ma'alei, but the closer to the edge the better and maybe
we would have put it right at the edge? So therefore you
needed
ואיצטריך דרב יעקב v'itztarich d'Rav Yaakov to tell you no, there's a
minimum you have to remove it from the edge, which is the
joint width. ואי מהא דרב יעקב, ve'ei me'ha d'Rav Yaakov, had it
been רב יעקב, Rav Yaakov, הוה אמינא מלא קשר גודל דלא ליקרב
טפי. hava amina melo kesher godel d'lo likrav tfei. It has to
be a, you know, the thumb joint removed from the edge, don't
get it any closer, right? That's the minimum distance. וכמה דרחיק מעלי,
vekhama d'rachik ma'alei, but maybe you would have thought there's no maximum?
You could get it very, very distant from the edge. צריכא, tzricha,
you need both. Okay, so that's very— very clear. One is giving
you a minimum, one is a maximum and that's exactly where we
put the hole of the ציצית. We'll try to wrap this up
now for today. We got a— we're getting a little ahead. רבינא
ורב סמא הוו יתבי קמיה דרב אשי. Ravina v'Rav Sama hava yasvei
kamey d'Rav Ashi. רבינא Ravina and רב סמא Rav Sama were sitting
in front of רב אשי. Rav Ashi. וחזיה רב סמא לקרנא דגלימא
דרבינא, v'chazya Rav Sama l'karna d'glima d'Ravina, and רב סמא Rav Sama
saw the corner of the garment of רבינא, Ravina, דסתר ובצא ממלא
קשר גודל, de'satar u'vatza m'melo kesher godel, that it was being a
little fraying, the corner, and now— or maybe רש״י Rashi says or
maybe the hole was growing, and now the ציצית were within— In
this thumb's width of the edge of the garment. Okay, so that's
a problem. אמר ליה, Amar lei, לא סבר ליה מר להא דרבי
יעקב? Lo savar lei Mar l'ha d'Rabbi Yaakov? Do you not hold
of what רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says? אמר ליה, Amar lei, so
he said back to him, בשעת עשייה איתמר. Bish'as asiyah itmar. No,
this requirement of minimum distance was when it was originally placed in
the garment. If after was placed the hole got bigger, the edge
got shorter, whatever and now it's closer to the edge, that's not
a problem. איכסיף, Ichsif, he was embarrassed. He thought he was correcting
him and it turns out that he was the one that was
wrong. אמר ליה רב אשי, Amar lei Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav
Ashi said to him, לא תתקף לך דא, Lo tatkif lach da,
don't let it be so difficult to you that you were wrong
and that he knew better than you. חד מינייהו כתריי מינן, Chad
mineihu kitrei minan, one of us from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is
better than two of you from בבל. Bavel. Of course you're not
going to know the הלכה halacha as well as we do. We're
better than you here in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. I don't know
how that exactly makes him feel better, but okay. Anyway, that is
the end of that discussion. We got a little ahead from being
a little behind and we will stop here for today.